[Music]
do
hello good evening good day everybody
and welcome to the latest episode of the
ask widget show
as you know today we discuss science i'm
taking your questions about science so
before we begin let me take a look at
who all is there
i can see
gk tejas jai ananya pranay komal
and
lots and lots of other people
great to be with you all once again
this fine saturday evening over here
so shall we get into the questions let's
begin with the questions
and what is the first question
the first question is by our friend
dungar sinchohan and the question is the
james webb telescope was hit by a number
of meteorites
in may which has led to some permanent
damage will it lead to some
significant deterioration in its
performance
okay so yes uh i'm not sure when this
happened but yes this telescope was hit
by
one
micrometeorite oh um yeah so
uh what's a micrometeorite a
micrometeorite is a meteorite a piece of
space rock which is less than a gram in
mass in weight
small very small okay so let's take a
look at what sort of damage this uh
telescope has suffered let me share my
screen
and uh let us do a search
for the jwst mirror
there we are there we are one second
give me a second
so this is what the james webb space
telescopes mirror looks like
it's a hexagonal arrangement as you can
see yeah it's it's a massive mirror
and it's made up of these segments
so a1 b1 a4 etc i think the segment that
was struck by the micro battery it was a
c3 segment the c3 segment was hit and it
suffered a small amount
of damage
so the thing about the james webb
telescope is that all of these different
segments can be aligned individually
they all have their own little motors
that align them and over the past few
months each of these mirror segments was
aligned in order to
to
be able to give a proper image
so in case so the jwst is designed such
that in case one or two or
several of these segments are damaged
they can be realigned using the motors
in order
to offset the the
the effect of the damage and it will
still be able to produce a reasonably
good image
so right now i believe that the
deterioration in the image quality is
insignificant
despite
uh this damage having occurred
so the thing is this the damage which
has happened is
permanent damage
it's not going to be repaired because
it's so far away the telescope is so far
away that nobody can go and repair it
and that's why this
mechanism is inbuilt into this
telescope that
if
one of these segments is damaged it can
be realigned and the overall image that
is produced is still going to be good
so i think it's not
a significant setback
the images that this telescope is
producing are still very much in
they are still exceeding
uh the desired outcome
uh of the expectations
so overall it's fine
so it's not a number of meteorites it is
a single
space rock and that to a micro meteorite
less than one gram
in uh in mass
so it is not going to lead to
significant deterioration in the
performance so the overall uh envisaged
lifetime the hoped for lifetime
the minimum lifetime for this telescope
is five years but it is expected it is
hoped that it will last for 20 years
hopefully
and
yeah they have obviously calculated the
effect the possible effect of
micrometeorite damage and all that into
all these calculations
so the so far so good it's still working
fine it's still going to give us great
results and we hope that there is no
more
at least for some time no more damage of
this kind yeah
okay master sensei gaming says as the us
is claiming to have found aliens
with its james webb telescope what is
your thought
on it
is already the japanese have claimed
that they have seen them many years ago
also many japanese have sent spend their
life to find aliens and document what
they found well if people have been
documenting aliens where are the aliens
show me
where are the aliens what's the
documentation where is the documentation
where's the proof
now this other claim that i'm hearing i
like what we're seeing here that the us
is claiming to have found aliens when
did the claim happen i have not seen any
such claim
i have seen many youtubers
including several
indian youtubers claiming that the james
webb
telescope has found life
or aliens
first evidence of alien life or
something like that where
i i failed to understand how people can
make such idiotic ridiculous
baseless claims
i've seen multiple youtubers making this
claim that the james webb space
telescope has found life
alien life
what nonsense
it's found no such thing
nobody has made these claims apart from
people who are completely
unconnected with this telescope
so
here's
how
this telescope could possibly
find
traces signatures or signs
of what could possibly be life
okay this telescope has got an infrared
spectrometer spectrograph whatever you
want to call it so what this instrument
does
is it
takes uh
images
of a
spectra
so let's say you are uh
and and this this
this spectrometer spectrograph can take
spectra from lots of different sources
at the same time
now what is a spectrum a light spectrum
it's like
a light library color library light
library so when you are taking the
spectrum for from let us say an
exoplanet which is a planet in orbit
around a distant star
so when you're taking the spectrum the
light signature the light library
from that exoplanet you are essentially
uh
cataloging the chemical signature the
signature the the chemical cocktail
of that exoplanet
so when light let's say
let's say you are looking at a forest
yeah on earth
you're looking at a forest or not what
you see
you see the color green
that's what you see now why do you see
the color green it's because the
chlorophyll that is in the leaves
of these
plants in trees
it absorbs light in the red spectrum
and blue spectrum it absorbs red light
and blue light and it reflects back
green light
that's why
forests and plants look green
now if you were an alien with their own
james webb telescope you are pointing it
at earth and collecting the light
spectrum you would see lots of blue and
green
and you would see the distinctive
signatures of something like chlorophyll
and whatever
uh composition we of gases we have in
our atmosphere right
so that's a light spectrum
and based on the spectrum these aliens
could come to the conclusion that there
is a very high likelihood of there being
life on this planet
because we find trace the signature of
chlorophyll and various other
uh
gases in the atmosphere which are
characteristic of a certain kind of life
right so similarly the james webb
telescope could look at other planets
exoplanets and if it finds certain such
signatures
that are the characteristic signatures
of earth like life then one could
say with
a reasonable amount of confidence that
there could be
possibly
life there so then we could make a
create a catalogue of such interesting
planets where there is a high likelihood
of light of life and then study them
further
with through a variety of means
so that is what the james webb space
telescope can do
it's not going to detect aliens and say
hey there's a photograph of 15 aliens
having a party it doesn't work like that
and thus far uh from the results that
have been released it has uh
uh
we have seen the result from a single
exoplanet thus far uh and that's that's
uh
a type of exoplanet called a hot jupiter
it's a it's called wolf something this
this particular exoplanet it's a hot
jupiter which means it's a jupiter-like
gas giant which is very in a very tight
orbit around its star which means it's
the orbit is very small it's uh the
distance between this exoplanet and its
star is is less than the distance of
mercury from our
star from the sun
so it's got a very short
orbit of orbital period three four days
at most and it's a very hot planet
and
the telescope has
examined the spectrum
of this planet and it's it's shown that
there is water water vapor on in this
planet's atmosphere and there are clouds
but obviously it's too hot to sustain
any kind of life
so this is what we have found thus far
a giant
gas giant hot jupiter kind of exoplanet
which contains
water in its atmosphere and obviously
there will be
clouds
so that's what we know that's far that
is not proof of life
that is not proof of life by any means
whatsoever so please understand that
there is no claim that has been made
of having found aliens or having found
life or any such thing right
so uh so please
keep things balanced don't
get carried away by sensational
reporting yeah
we are still
a long way away from finding any aliens
but yes so that's the potential that
this telescope has it will be able to
identify interesting exoplanets where we
should look further because there could
be life there yeah so that's uh what
this telescope can do
thus far we we are in the beginning of
the of the uh
of the career of this telescope so so
the so let me set the record straight we
have not found aliens thus far at least
now i don't know what the japanese have
been claiming
there is this entire industry that is
built around
you know
the alien
visitation industry there are lots of
people in various countries who
are alien hunters or whatever and they
claim they have met aliens or they've
been abducted by aliens so they have
found aliens and what not
where is the evidence
there's none
so
and and since we are talking about
aliens let's take one more question
about aliens this is from quite some
time ago a month ago but let's take a
look anyway
so this is by rani
uh the question is the news broke out
last year about an ex-israeli space
chief admitting the existence of aliens
it was said that both the u.s and israel
have some kind of contact with aliens
and allegedly donald trump
also knows about this and was prohibited
to expose the news to the public because
people aren't ready yet
what's your take on this whole situation
do you think the two countries are
working together with aliens or are
these made-up stories for maybe some
other purpose my question is very simple
why would aliens only contact the u.s
every time the claims of alien
whatever contact happen it's the u.s
when you see ufos it's always in
american skies
very soon we'll see ufos with mcdonald's
advertising
pizza hut advertising on them because
you know
because these are american companies
the question is why do ufos only appear
in american skies why do aliens only
visit the us and maybe israel now why
why why
aliens don't care about human politics
do they they wouldn't know they would
not know anything about it and if they
do visit the earth they should be
visible
in all countries in all major countries
um i've yet to see any indians claiming
uh to have seen
ufos
or have been having been abducted by
aliens i've not i've not seen any claims
from india or china by the for that
matter so why only the u.s and now
israel is getting involved in this so
yes i did see the news i did read about
this that uh one of the ex-israeli i
don't know some kind of prominent person
in israel who's now retired claimed that
they they have some kind of they have
some kind of contact with aliens
so once again that is a claim please
understand
the difference between a claim
and proof
if i say i have shook i have shaken
hands with aliens it is a claim it's a
claim i am making a claim verbal claim
i am not showing you
a photograph
or a video of me shaking hands with
aliens so if this gentleman is claiming
that he or his agency or his country is
in contact with aliens
why doesn't he furnish
evidence
convincing evidence
right in undisputable evidence
photographic evidence
video evidence or why doesn't it produce
an alien for an interview
they won't do that
uh you know these these uh
spy chiefs at spies they have a sense of
humor
they have a sense of humor and
you know it's it's fun to
throw in a few stories to to
to get the media
buzzing
so my my take on this is very simple as
long as there is no evidence i will not
believe it
this is that's how it works
you if you make an extraordinary claim
you have to produce evidence
extraordinary evidence for any claim
to be taken seriously
there has to be evidence to back up the
claim
show me the evidence i have yet to see
evidence i would be the happiest person
in the world
if uh alien
contact is proven or it happens i'll be
the happiest person in the world i mean
when i was a kid i was obsessed with
aliens and ufos and i i really wish that
this would happen and it would meet us
other other
civilizations and establish contact and
cultural enrichment or whatever
so yeah i'll be the happiest person in
the world
but yeah i have never found a single
piece of evidence that has
that would convince me so i am very
skeptical
but i am hopeful
that's my take on this
ananya says
pranam
why are all scorpions fluorescent what a
great question
so let's take a look at what she means
by this
uh let me share my screen scorpions
fluorescent one second
fluorescence so scorpions uh are
creatures as you know they are very
scary creatures they have this
uh
stinger as you can see once again let me
share my screen where is it where is it
here we are
so the scorpions
we know what they are right so they glow
in the moonlight
and they grow they glow in ultraviolet
light
so if you go out in the night
in a desert or wherever and you have an
ultraviolet torch light
then you'll be able to detect scorpions
very easily because this is what it
looks like the glow
they glow in ultraviolet light and also
in moonlight moonlight seems to have
some kind of ultraviolet component
so this is what it looks like it's a
fascinating phenomenon and what's even
more interesting
is that
fossilized
scorpions
and some spiders also apparently
fossilized spiders
also seem to glow
in ultraviolet light fossils
so the question is why are all these
scorpions arachnids
scorpions why are they fluorescent
so uh
they are fluorescent because there is
some kind of fluorescent molecule or
molecules or compounds
that are present in their uh
exoskeleton
on the on the external part of the body
so i think scorpions they they mold they
shed their outer skin
every few i don't know periodically i
suppose i don't know what is the period
so uh the fluorescent molecular compound
or compounds whatever it is is present
in the exoskeleton of this of the
scorpions
now what is the reason
why it is so why what is the purpose of
this glow so maybe
we don't quite know it has not been
conclusively demonstrated why this sort
of evolutionary
adaptation has happened
but several theories have been thrown
out thrown about for example it is
speculated that possibly this
fluorescent molecules are compounds it
protects the scorpions from parasites
perhaps or maybe it acts as some kind of
a sunscreen or maybe it helps them
find mates in the dark or in the light
possibly some kind of such thing maybe
it has anti-fungal properties maybe it's
a kind of sunblock it protects them from
some from
sun
maybe it confuses the prey of the
scorpion and makes the prey easier to
catch yeah maybe it makes scorpions
easier maybe it makes it easier for
scorpions to recognize each other maybe
if they're the same species of scorpion
they have a similar glow whatever
yeah or maybe it's some kind of
relic trait from an earlier age in which
it was useful maybe it's not useful no
we don't quite know
lots of
such theories have been uh
proposed put forward but we still don't
have the conclusive answer what we do
know is that this is a fascinating
phenomenon and there are i i cannot
think of any other species of animal or
creature or whatever life form that has
this very interesting evolutionary
adaptation
so that's what i can say
they do fluoresce they the fluorescence
is caused by
uh
maybe some kind of molecule or molecules
or compounds and we don't know quite
what the purpose is
so that's what i can tell you about this
alpha beta says why are why octopus
why are octopuses octopi
so fascinating
probably better than humans in some
scenarios do they have extraterrestrial
origin
okay let's bring the octopus on the
screen octopus o c
g o p u s let me google that and put
octopuses
on the screen what do they look like
this is what octopuses look like yeah
this is how they are picturized in
cartoons but the real octopus
octopuses octopi come in a variety of
species in variety of sizes people even
eat them
yeah in japan and in spain
and various other cultures yes it's a
delicacy and octopuses are are
very strange creatures they have eight
eight arms or eight legs whatever you
want to call them they've got these very
interesting looking eyes
and
they are very intelligent creatures they
they come in very small sizes and large
sizes as well
there are like very massive large
octopuses as well certain species
and so on so what makes these creatures
fascinating are do they have alien
origin first of all no they do not have
extraterrestrial origin but they are
very strange alien looking creatures
deep they live in the oceans in the seas
i don't think there are any fresh water
octopuses as far as i know
so what are the interesting things about
octopuses first of all the
number of
neurons
an octopus has
is approximately the same as the number
of neurons that a dog has
that kind of tells you that the octopus
is a very intelligent creature
it could have the same kind of
intelligence that a dog has and as we
know dogs are very intelligent creatures
right
octopuses and
the interesting thing is that the
octopus
essentially has nine different brains
each of its arms
has what you could call its own brain
it they are the creature also has a
central brain which is located in the in
the head region yeah
and the central brain is able to to
uh
overall
control the various arms but the arms
also have an autonomous component they
can operate autonomously in certain
cases so this creature essentially has a
distributed brain or what you could even
regard as nine different brains that's
one thing
and octopuses are most likely able to
recognize human faces they're very
intelligent they can tell one human
being from another
and they can
develop likes and dislikes towards
different people some people they will
like very much some people they will
dislike based on various behavior
behaviors that people have exhibited and
so on
that sort of thing and octopuses are
they
they kind of are known to pull pranks on
people so there was this interesting uh
story that came out of a
researched lab or or aquarium or
something there was an octopus in a tank
right an octopus inside a tank and there
were in a room
and there was another tank in the room
which contained fish now what happened
is that the fish were disappearing
over a period of several days
and nobody understood where the fish
were going because the fish are in one
tank the octopus is in a different tank
now what these people did is that they
put a security camera in the room
and they left it on
the next day when they came they
discovered that the octopus was going
out of it was opening the lid of its
tank
going outside walking on the floor
climbing up and opening the tank
opening the lid of the tank that
contained the fish
going inside catching a fish eating it
then going out of the tank closing the
lid and climbing back into its tank
and he was hiding the evidence of what
he did or she did whatever right so
that's the kind of uh incredibly
intelligent behavior that octopuses
exhibit
right so these are some of the
interesting characteristics that
octopuses have
very intelligent
animals the kind of intelligence they
they have is similar to that of dogs the
the
most intelligent animals non-human
animals that we know of are
dolphins
and dogs and cats obviously
dogs are said to be more intelligent and
we also could consider crows and parrots
to be quite intelligent
these animals they exhibit a
tool making or tool using behavior
so even octopuses have been observed to
use tools
they are used shells
you know sea shells as tools they
collect sea shells sea shells
and stack stack them together and use
them again as defenses against other
organisms other creatures or as
in order to break the currents of the
ocean they even use coconut shells for
various purposes they collect them stack
them together so they have been observed
in this sort of exhibiting this sort of
behavior tool collection and to use so
overall very interesting
creature looks very alien it's it's very
different from anything we would
typically observe or interact with
and yeah so that's what it is and
they have a very strange blood i think
it's a
we humans and most animals mammals
uh lizards etc reptiles etc
our blood contains hemoglobin
in the case of octopuses the their blood
contains hemocyanin which is essentially
blue
our blood is red their blood is bluish
or whitish so
lots of
differences very alien looking creature
so that's that's why octopuses are so
fascinating and they are they are the
subject of study
um very interesting creatures and very
little understood very intelligent
so that's why
they are fascinating i'm not sure if
they're better or worse than humans i
mean how do you qualitatively compare
two such different species what
what is the criterion for being better
or worse i'm not sure so i would not say
it's better or worse but it's really
fascinating very intelligent
and
yeah
so
intelligent and interesting
species of of animal
okay aditya narayan pandey says
i think
mars's ice will automatically melt in
the upcoming 100 to 200 years
since the sun is slowly slowly becoming
a red giant
because of conversion of hydrogen into
helium
and due to this many unknown creatures
may come back in survival mode on mars
maybe humans till the time would have
left the earth or human race would have
come to an end due to unbearable
temperature of upgraded version of the
sun red giant
and then unknown creatures come alive on
mars
so
in 100 or 200 years
the sun is going to become a red giant
this really hurts my feelings
listen
the sun is not going to become a red
giant in the next couple of centuries
it's going to take five billion years
five with nine zeros after it
all right
it's not going to happen next week or
next year or next century
in 200 years it's not going to be the
end of the solar system please please
understand these are
very large time scales we are talking
about
our sun is about 5 billion years old
it's got another 5 billion years left in
it
right
and uh yeah so uh
so this is not gonna happen in the next
hundred to two hundred years
uh yeah it will eventually become a red
giant it will eventually die a slow
lingering kind of demise its outer
layers will just fl will just waft off
into outer space is going to give rise
to what's what's called
incorrectly a planetary nebula
something like
uh
i can't think of the names right now but
yeah the one of the recent images of the
jwst shows what's called a planetary
nebula
uh and eventually what will be left at
the core of the sun is
what's called a white dwarf so that's
what's going to happen that's going to
happen over a very long period of time
five
billion years
right so
not a couple of centuries no sir
no sir
and the process is quite complicated and
you could simplify it but i've i've done
that
multiple times i'm not going to go into
that right now how it happens
and now what you're talking about in
unknown creatures survival mode on mars
i mean we don't have any evidence
of any life on mars there could have
been life in the past no doubt about it
mars was a very nice
wet planet very similar to what the
earth is
that was about four four and uh about
four billion years before today right
and then things happened and things
changed and it became a
dry
barren planet
so uh we know there is ice on mars there
is subsurface water most likely on mars
but there is no evidence of life but the
main point i would like to make is that
the sun is not going to become a red
giant in 200 years it's gonna take five
billion or so years it will start in a
billion years or so it will start
expanding and so and all that but there
is plenty of time left plenty of time
all right
okay since we're talking about mars
crazy brain says everyone is going is
eyeing to go to mars
you mentioned that if someone somehow
we're able to heat up and melt the
remaining ice on the planet then maybe a
hospitable environment can be created my
question is if the core itself of mars
has cooled down and doesn't have a
magnetic field
how can a hospitable atmosphere be
created by melting ice all right
so you are correct
mars does not have a strong magnetic
field it has a very weak
remnant of what used to be a good
magnetic field
so the earth over our planet has a
strong reasonably strong magnetic field
why does it have it
it's because of the dynamo effect that
is caused by the interior of the earth
what does the interior of the earth look
like
uh let me see
let me put that on the screen the
interior part of the earth so the earth
the interior of the earth is something
like this right the various layers
of the earth
so at the very center of the earth and
in the interior layers of the earth so
we have the crust and the mantle yeah
the stiffer mantle etc then you have the
outer core of the earth which is liquid
and the inner core which is solid and
there's a magma layer and all that so
the outer core
is liquid metal it's mostly iron and
possibly nickel and some other it's a
mixture of metals mostly iron and the
inner core is solid so when you have a
massive
core made up of molten metal which is
hot
and which is flowing
the flowing metal
conducts electricity and the the
moving charges
create a magnetic field because of the
dynamo effect very simple college level
school level high school level physics i
suppose right so that is why the earth
has a magnetic field now why is the
interior of the earth so hot and molten
and all that it's because of the heat
left over from the formation of the
solar system everything was shockingly
hot at the time right
and the earth formed out of a molten
ball of molten rock and metal and all
that the heaviest parts moved to the
center that's why it's got a metallic
center
and the heat is still very much present
in the interior of the earth which is
the heat left over from the formation of
the solar system and much of the heat
inside the earth is also produced by
radioactivity and things like that let's
not go into that
so the earth has a molten
core and a solid inner core and that's
why there's a magnetic field in the case
of mars mars is a much smaller planet
it cooled down
very rapidly compared to the earth which
is still very hot inside and because it
cooled down and the core of the planet
became solid so there are no more moving
charges and that's why the magnetic
field died out
right so the planet doesn't have
a anything
like the magnetic field of the earth
now
why is the magnetic field important
the earth's magnetic field let us take a
look at that earth magnetic field
earth's magnetic field
for the earth's magnetic field what it
does is that it deflects away the solar
wind what is the solar wind
okay
what is the solar wind the solar wind is
this uh
big wind of plasma that comes from the
sun
the sun emits plasma
and that
is what we call the solar wind this is
what it looks like kind of the the
representation of that
and this solar wind is essentially uh
is essentially
protons neutrons
uh
helium nuclei and so on is there a
problem with the image one second let me
see
give me a second to to fix that it looks
like there's a problem with the image
with the connection
hopefully it's fine no it's not fine yet
please give me a minute let me try to
fix this issue
it's a little blurred some people are
saying
that is
not great
hopefully it should be fine now
uh can you guys tell me if you are able
to see me fine or is it still blurred
there is a bit of lag is it blurring
can you all see me i think it's fine now
all right
okay so uh apologies for that little
little problem
so the solar wind is this wind of plasma
that comes from the sun it is a
a bunch of particles protons neutrons
uh
helium nuclei etc and what this does is
that it is very dangerous
uh it can strip away the atmosphere of a
planet which is not protected by a
magnetic field so in the case of the
earth the magnetic field of the earth
deflects away
this plasma the solar wind and one of
the effects of that is that we see
auroras right auroras in the north pole
region and the south pole region
but the atmosphere is protected from the
solar wind because of the magnetic field
of the earth which acts as a shield of
sorts
in the case of mars the magnetic field
isn't there and therefore the solar wind
directly
bombards the atmosphere of mars and
because of this the atmosphere of mars
slowly was stripped away and that's why
mars has a very thin atmosphere today
it's it's got a very thin tenuous kind
of atmosphere much thinner than that of
earth
it still does have an atmosphere but
it's not nowhere like the kind of
atmosphere that we have on the earth
and that is why mars became mars lost
all its water and all of it it became a
very dry and
added planet it's got water under the
surface and so on so that's the reason
why it is that way now
the thing is if we are able to somehow
heat up the planet let's say we
construct an array of mirrors gigantic
mirrors
around the planet
not completely around the planet it will
not envelop the planet entirely but it
will this array of mirrors will focus
more sunlight on the surface that could
heat up the planet it could uh
melt the ice
and it could create this water vapor and
all that it could change the atmosphere
the planet make it make the atmosphere
thicker and so on
and that's the process of terraforming
or maybe you could nuke the poles like
some people say
and that could uh do the thing
so uh yeah you could create over time a
more hospitable environment a thicker
atmosphere over time it could take maybe
a thousand years
so the question is the the core of the
planet has cooled down there is no
magnetic field then how can you sustain
a hospitable atmosphere the thing is
this
you can sustain
a thick atmosphere for a few million
years
maybe 10 million years maybe 100 million
the effect of the solar wind on the
atmosphere of stripping away at the
atmosphere
is a slow process it doesn't happen in a
week or a month or a year or even a
century it may take a few million years
so if you can create a thick atmosphere
at a fast rate
then
you could have a nice hospitable
habitable planet
and and this uh
scenario will last for a few million
years maybe a million years maybe 10
maybe 100 which is perfectly great for
us
our species is at most
a quarter
or a third
of a million years old so for us a
million years is like forever
so
so we have to look at the time scales
and put that into the right context and
perspective right so it won't last
forever we know that but it will
probably last longer than
how
than the age of our species thus far so
which is which is perfectly good for us
so that's why we talk about doing this
but we're still very far from doing that
we still don't have the technology to
first of all reach there in sufficient
numbers and secondly to terraform the
planet so it's all in the future but
it's possible
okay kabir singh says
what is so special about homo sapiens
the history of humans on earth is more
than a million years
so why
are why were other species not able to
do remarkable advancements like the
modern humans
or is it the mystery please answer so as
far as we know
we are the most intelligent and advanced
species that has ever existed on our
planet as far as we know
we have seen the entire fossil record
whatever is available to us and from all
of that we have concluded that we have
we are the most advanced species that is
that has ever existed on the planet now
it's entirely possible like joe rogan
would say
that there could have been other
civilizations on this planet maybe 100
million years ago maybe a half a billion
years ago and we have lost all trace of
that
because the surface of the planet is
geologically
active
there is tectonic movement
yeah and all that so what happens is
that
over time over millions of years
the
entire
topology geology of the earth changes
what is on the surface goes deep
underground and what is deep underground
comes this to the surface it's an
ever-changing environment an
ever-changing surface but the changes
happen over very long geological time
scales
so if an advanced civilization advanced
species existed maybe 500 million years
ago
it's entirely possible that there would
be no trace left of that
whatever traces exist would have been
buried deep deep deep
kilometers on the ground and we may
never ever find that
so that is one possibility
right
that such a species other species may
have existed but we have lost all uh
traces of that
now
but as far as we know from all the
evidence that we have discovered thus
far we are the most advanced species so
the question is what is so special about
homo sapiens what makes us special
the history of humans on earth is more
than a million years well
if you take the entire
uh
lineage of archaic humans
proto-humans etc yeah it's about two
million years uh our our ancestors there
they split up from the ancestors of the
chimpanzees about i think about two
million years before today
and the common ancestors of humans and
chimpanzees split up from the ancestors
of gorillas i believe about six
million years before today 60 lakh yeah
so it's not a very
long period of time
so what makes humans special right
the first thing
that makes humans special
is opposing
thumbs
you see opposing thumbs
uh
we can pinch each of our fingers in this
manner with our thumbs there is no other
species of well monkeys can do it
so that is what makes the the monkeys
the primates
different from other species right
this this property no apart from
primates apart from monkeys no no other
group of animals
has this property to be able to pinch
like this so this gave humans and
monkeys the ability the dexterity to
create tools and to manipulate their
environment
in a variety of ways that other animals
can't do i mean
if a dog has an itch on his back or on
his back he cannot reach around and
scratch himself can he he has to go and
scratch his back against a tree or
something
so that's one thing the second thing is
bipedalism
for some reason
humans became bipedal animals it's
extremely unnatural to walk
on two feet
all animals most animals walk on four
four legs right
dogs cats bears um
bears are a special kind of dog
i mean look at the face of a bear it
looks like that of a dog right so a bear
is like a massive dog and bears actually
can walk on two legs if they want to
when they when they when they feel like
but typically if you see bears running
and walking and ambling around they do
it in four legs
and bears also have a certain amount of
dexterity and intelligence
so the thing is this when you walk on
two legs when you walk upright your head
your face your eyes are much higher up
from the ground and you can see much
further away
right if you can see much further away
your brain your mind has to process much
more information
and that
in a way could induce your brain to
develop more your cranial capacity to
increase and that obviously is is
something that gives rise to
higher intelligence
of course one can find other examples
like giraffes
that have not developed higher
intelligence but giraffes don't have
opposing thumbs
so the ability to create tools the
ability to be extremely dexterous with
your hands the ability to see far away
the ability to walk upright
these are things and then you have the
spectroscopic vision
if you see birds eagles etc if you see
dogs cats
not dogs and cats but birds for instance
they have eyes on the side of the sides
of the heads fish have eyes on the sides
of the heads so they cannot see in 3d
humans have eyes right here so we can
see in in depth 3d so a multitude of
factors came together and created this
perfect storm that gave rise to the
intelligent apes apes in suits
there are humans we are genetically
extremely close extremely similar to
chimpanzees and gorillas and bonobos as
well
extremely close uh the genetic
difference between humans and
chimpanzees is about one percent
99 approximately roughly
of our genes are the same and yet we are
so different we are far more intelligent
um apart from that physically we are
extremely unremarkable
you could be six feet tall you could be
a bodybuilder you could be arnold
schwarzenegger and yet a chimpanzee who
is half a size is physically going to be
stronger than you
so humans are incredibly weak as animals
we can't run fast
dogs cats
can run faster than us
the chimpanzees can run faster than us
bears can run faster than us who are so
large and fat
humans are incredibly weak
and yet the super power we have is our
intelligence we are the apex
predator in our planet we are the super
predator
the most dangerous animal
that exists and we have taken over the
planet
haven't we
so these are the things that make homo
sapiens special and different from all
others
so that's what it is it's a whole
combination of factors that came
together to produce this this remarkably
intelligent and extremely dangerous
species
ananya says
as
such plants look passive but we know
that they have life
do they also have their own sensory
system designed to respond to danger or
other changes in their environment do
plants talk to each other pranam all
right
plants obviously are living beings we
know that for sure plants grow plants
die plants have life cycles and so on
plants are living beings you know that
um they do
respond to external stimuli not in real
time as we do
plants don't have muscles they they have
their own
uh
internal systems they have sap they have
parenchyma they have chlorine karma they
have a
whole
it's it's botany we are zoology they are
botany right
plants do respond to changes in the
external exterior environment they do
respond to stimuli
so
if you see sunflowers for instance
sunflowers typically face the sun as the
sun moves through the sky
over a 12 12 hour or so period the
sunflower
moves it kind of tracks the sun
you see plants when it's night their
leaves close down when it's daytime they
can sense the light has come out and the
leaves open up right you can see that
um
in a forest if you if you see a time
lapse you will see the trees try try to
stay out of each other's personal zones
they all try to keep some distance
between each other
that sort of movement you can see and so
on so plants definitely do respond to
external stimuli if a plant is under
attack
by from some predator they have defense
mechanisms that get activated when some
part of the plant is eaten up right if
let's say you have a plant which has a
certain kind of defense mechanism and
some animal a grazing animal comes and
starts stomping on it then it will
activate that defense mechanism and some
sort of response will be seen
so plants do respond
to the external environment they do seem
to have some kind of sensory system not
the kind of sensory system that we we
have
i'm not sure if they feel pain if they
don't even have a central nervous system
or such
so the concept of pain most likely
doesn't exist with plants
but
they do respond
they do
perceive threats and respond accordingly
and so on i don't know if plants can
communicate with each other for
communication you need intelligence for
communication you need a brain a central
nervous system
plants don't have anything like that
they have a distributed system of
sensory inputs and all
so it doesn't appear like plants talk to
each other there have been experiments
done about the response of plants to
music you play horrible noisy sounds to
plants they don't grow very well
over a period of weeks if you play
pleasant music to them they grow better
so yeah there is some something
something out there we don't quite know
yet and that's one of the mystery right
so that's a big mystery uh
we is so much that science doesn't
understand clearly there is some kind of
uh
relationship between the kind of sounds
that you
[Music]
uh expose a plant to in the way the
plant grows
and somehow nice melodious music makes
plants grow better and healthier so
there is something there but we don't
quite know what it is
that's a mystery
okay sarthak says
we know that when a particle of
antimatter
and matter
comes together
they completely annihilate each other
but what about the neutrons in both
particles are the neutrons of an
anti-oxygen atom the same as the
neutrons of a normal oxygen atom
if yes then do they still annihilate
each other this is an extremely good
question very intelligent question
so
uh like i have explained in the past
antimatter
is
the difference between antimatter and
matter is that certain properties in
antimatter are the opposite for instance
the regular proton
has an antimatter counterpart the
antiproton now the antiproton
the regular proton is positively charged
the antiproton is negatively charged
the electron
has an antimatter particle uh antimatter
comp
antimatter counterpart called the
positron the regular electron is
negatively charged the positron is
positively charged but it has the same
mass
so proton antiproton
electron
positron what about the neutron the
neutron has no charge
so does it mean and we know that the
photon is its own antiparticle the
photon is a different thing it's a boson
um
so what about the neutron
the neutron is is neutral so is the
neutron its owner in the particle no not
quite so the neutrons anti-particle is
the anti-neutron the anti-neutron now
what is the difference
the difference is the quark composition
of the neutron and the anti-neutron so
in the case of the neutron you have one
up quark and two down quarks
udd
is the comp is the quark composition of
a neutron
in the case of an anti-neutron you have
three anti-quarks
u-bar
d bar anti up anti up quark anti down
quark and anti down quark it's a it's a
triplet of quarks
so
that is the difference
a neutron is made up of regular quarks
an anti neutron is made up of
anti-quarks
that is the difference but yes both are
neutrally charged they don't have any
electric charge and if they come into
contact with it with each other they
will instantaneously annihilate each
other
so it's a good question so you need to
dig deeper when it comes to neutrons and
anti-neutron it's just not just the
charges it's the quark composition
and anti-neutrons have anti-quarks apart
from that they look just the same as as
regular neutrons but you bring them
together neutron and neutron they will
annihilate each other into pure energy
excellent
question
okay
rajat says in the schodinger equation
there is a presence of
the imaginary
the the i right square root of minus 1.
why is it so does it mean that the
quantum state the quantum nature can
only be defined by complex numbers
please shed some light
this is a very good question so let me
uh
try and explain what is the meaning of
all of this
so
you may know
hopefully that the schrodinger equation
is a wave
equation
it it
it describes a wave
what kind of wave probability wave the
probability of a particle being in a
certain place
at a certain time
in the tdac time dependent ordinary
equation so the probability of a
particle being
being found in a certain place
and the the whole
that so that is that is the probability
and the whole
set of probabilities is the whole
chronicle equation it's a wave equation
it's a wave now what is a wave
think about a sine wave
a sine wave looks like that right it's a
sine wave
and
any wave can be thought of
as a superposition of a variety of sine
waves and cosine waves you put them
together in a superposition you get any
kind of wave you can create any kind of
wave or any kind of shape from a
superposition of sines and cosines sine
waves and cosine waves of different
amplitudes and frequencies and all of
that
now
have you heard of the euler identity
euler
one of the uh
one of the ways of looking at it is is
like this let me share my screen
and let's take a look at this
let's take a look at this
so you can represent sines and cosines
in this manner
the cosine of x is the real part of e
raised to i x
which is e raised to i x plus plus
series to minus i x divided by 2 and the
sine of x is the imaginary part of e
raised to i x which is e raised to i x
minus e raised to minus ix upon 2i right
now we know that sines and cosines are
very much real
it's not imaginary
but it can be represented in this manner
it's a more
and it it all comes out of the complex
plane which is represented like this and
you can see why
e raised to i theta is cos cos theta
plus i sine theta
so
there is a variety of ways
of representing sines and cosines one of
the ways of doing it is through by using
imaginative numbers and that is kind of
the reason why
there is
the i in the schrodinger equation this
holding the equation is a wave equation
and in wave equation in any kind of wave
equation you can always have
imaginary numbers it doesn't mean that
it's an imaginary equation of course you
need to take the
uh modulus to get an actual
result and so on but
so i hope that explains why it is so
it's because it's a very big question
and waves can be represented as sines
and cosines or a superposition of sines
and cosines and when you have sines and
cosines you can
have
the
i square root of minus 1
in the mathematical formulation so that
should should kind of give you some kind
of idea as to why
the show the schrodinger equation has
the eye that's not the exact answer but
it's an analog kind of analogy to help
you understand why it is so to
understand why
the equation is the way it is you need
to see how it is derived which is a
whole different story i will not go into
that right now but think of it this way
and it will help you understand why
there is the i in there
all right let's go next question
how can we make ballistic missiles
maneuver
just like hypersonic missiles all right
hypersonic signs
so first of all let's talk about what a
hypersonic missile is what's a
hypersonic missile
what is the speed of sound
the speed of sound is 333 343 meters per
second yeah
0.34 kilometers
per second yeah that is the speed of
sound
an intercontinental ballistic missile
icbm
has a speed of about
mach 20 mach 21 what is mach 1 mach 1 is
the speed of sound which is 0.34
kilometers per second
um icbm intercontinental
intercontinental ballistic missile
travels at let's say mach 20 20 times
the speed of sound that's how incredibly
fast it goes
now when we talk about supersonic
hypersonic supersonic speed is from mach
1.2 to mach 5 which is 1.2 times the
speed of sound to about 5 times the
speed of sound that is the supersonic
range
hypersonic is between
mach 5 and mach 10 5 times to 10 times
the speed of sound
high hypersonic is between mach 10 and
mach 25 and then there is re-entry speed
which is more than mach 25 which is when
you you have missile re-entry or or you
know re-entry of spacecraft into the
earth's atmosphere
so these are the different
speed ranges so when we require talking
about hypersonic it's typically between
mach 5 and mac 10
icbms are in the high hypersonic range
now the question is how do we make
ballistic missiles maneuver like
hypersonic missiles well i suppose
you're talking about cruise missiles in
the case of various cruise missiles
let's say you have the brahmos which is
a supersonic missile it is a missile
that can maneuver and evade counter
measures you also have
other kinds of hypersonic missiles uh
which have maneuverable
uh characteristics right
so how do we make ballistic missiles
maneuver so there is something called a
maneuver
maneuverable re-entry vehicle marv
before we talk about marvel let's talk
about mi rv multiple independently
targetable reentry vehicles mirv
so when you have a ballistic missile you
can put multiple warheads
in that missile and when it re-enters
the atmosphere after its parabolic
trajectory which takes it out of the
atmosphere when it re-enters the
atmosphere you can make each of these
warheads go in independent directions so
a single missile can deliver let's say
warheads to 10 different locations which
makes it very hard to intercept right so
a number of
mirv equipped missiles exist like the
well
in india we have the agni p which was uh
tested i think in 21 last year
it was tested i believe with two
warheads
and those were not just mirv warheads
those were marv warheads
maneuverable re-entry vehicle which
means that these individual warheads
were capable of maneuvering not just
going straight down but maneuvering and
evading
measures
so uh that's so that's the marb
technology
and these these
maneuverable warheads will have certain
control surfaces
right that will that can allow them
which is like fins
or like small winglets
which you see on missiles which allow
them to to go in different directions
and eventually read the target reach the
target in a way that is not predictable
by the counter measures system or the
missile defense system
so this technology already exists right
so that is the marv technology you also
have hypersonic glide vehicles which use
boost
boost glide trajectories
it kind of doubles the the range or the
purely ballistic
missile trajectory there is something
called skip glide and skip re-entry etc
which could extend the range of the
missile even more it makes the path of
the missile very unpredictable you don't
quite know where it's going to come from
and once it re-enters from some angle
that you don't expect after that it may
even maneuver further before it reaches
the target so it makes it extremely
difficult for any missile defense system
to intercept that missile so
there is a russian hypersonic glide
vehicle called the avant-garde which is
already deployed then you have
chinese glide vehicles car like the dfzf
i think it's called or it was called the
wwu 14 or something
a chinese hypersonic glide vehicle
india is also
testing such technologies so india now
has mi rv technology marv technology the
agni p has been tested with that the
agni 5 the agni 6 most likely also has
this capability and so does the k5 k6 a
system of family of missiles and so on
so that's what we do
so these are
different classes of weapons
and these are in the high hypersonic
range
right
when you talk about hypersonic missiles
you most likely talking about cruise
missiles
like the zircon cruise missile or the
next generation brahmos missile or
whatever those are in the hypersonic
range
ballistic missiles and re-entry vehicles
etc are in the high hypersonic range
extremely high speeds mach 20 or maybe
slightly more than that
so that is how it is done it's a very
interesting field of aerodynamics not
very technically
well
technically it's it's simple enough but
to make it work it's really hard so
you have a whole
family of technologies that that go into
making this work and it's it's
you did a lot of testing as with
any technology
okay next question karthik srinivas says
could the universe be flat
would the universe be flat so what do we
mean by flat
the universe is three-dimensional
four-dimensional if you look at general
relativity so what does it mean when you
say
the universe is flat let's say i have a
book it is flat we know it's flat it's
two dimensional it's its surface is two
dimensional it is flat but what do we
mean by the flatness of the universe
doesn't make any sense
think about it like this
think of okay let me show an image it's
always better to show images to make a
sense of things
okay so we talk about different shapes
of the universe now you see this it
makes a little bit of sense
and yet we know that the universe is
four dimensional it has got four
dimensions three dimensions of of space
and one dimension of time
four dimensions but this is an analogy
so we know
from general relativity
that the presence of mass
curves space time forget about the
fourth dimension time for now think
about the three dimensions of space
right
so when you have mass it curves space
time so if you shine a ray of light that
ray of light will not travel in a
straight line it will travel in a curved
path
right
so
let's say you have
take a look at the topmost image where
it says flat
let's say you have a triangle
and each
side of this triangle is let's say a
hundred light years long
a light year is a distance
is a unit of distance the amount of
distance a light
ray a photon travels in a year so let's
say each arm of this triangle is let's
say a hundred light years long and you
have three spacecraft
at each
corner
of the triangle
now let's say these spacecraft that they
shine light beams or laser beams at each
other and that is what creates this red
triangle
if there is mass
present in the space
then these beams of light will not be
straight they will be curved and in the
real universe you have this curvature
in in
in space
so if you look at the universe at small
scales
10 light years 100 light years thousand
light years there is a lot of curvature
right and the universe is not flat
because light doesn't travel in straight
lines in in at small distances
but
if you travel very large distances
parsecs kiloparsecs megaparsecs the
universe looks remarkably flat
at small distances light travels in in
curved lines but at very very very large
distances
light travels reasonably flat
right light travels in a straight line
so the universe appears to be flat now
what do you mean by by flatness
uh one of the simple ways of looking at
flatness and curvature is this
in
a positively curved topology like the
one you see down here
the one you see down here
in a curved topology let's say let's
okay let me let me give you a different
analogy
let's say you are on the surface of the
earth all right
let me share the map even though we are
doing science today
so here we are this is the
planet let's say you are sitting on the
equator at gabon
and you start going and let's say you
have built a bridge
along the entire equator of the planet
planet and you start walking or you
start going on a plane or on a train or
whatever eastwards you start from gabon
on the equator you go keep going
eastwards you reach indonesia you keep
going further east you go keep going
further east you go to ecuador you cross
south america and you will eventually
end up in the same place
because
the surface of the earth is not flat it
is curved
right the surface of the earth is curved
now we know from geometry that when you
have a triangle
the sum of the interior angles of a
triangle is 360 degrees yes
yes the sum of the interior angles of a
triangle is 360 degrees but that only
works in flat space if you make a
triangle if you draw a triangle on the
surface of the earth
you will find that the sum of the angles
interior angle of the triangle is going
to exceed
360 degrees
so that is curved space all right
now let us come back to the diagram that
we had
here we are
so on a curved surface
you will find that the
sum of the interior angles of the
triangle is going to exceed
360 degrees in a negatively curved
topology you will find that the sum of
the angles is going to be less than 360
degrees and only in a flat topology it
is exactly equal to 360 degrees let's
take a different look at this
in flat space where there is no
curvature
parallel lines remain apart all the way
to infinity
in positive curvature
parallel lines converge they will
eventually converge together they will
meet
and in negative curvature
parallel lines will diverge from each
other right
so this is something we can test in the
universe you can actually test it and
what we find is that the universe or
very large
uh regions of regions of space is
completely flat
there is no curvature
that's what we find that is what we have
discovered thus far
the universe seems to be remarkably flat
which seems to indicate
which seems to indicate that the
universe could be infinite in
size because if there was curvature it
means that the universe is a finite size
no matter how small the curvature is if
there is any amount of curvature it
means it could be spherical and it may
have a finite size but since it is
completely flat from whatever we have
seen it could indicate that the universe
is in finite it never ends
so
our means of measuring all these
different
things is is our means are very
rudimentary we are a very
technologically primitive species
we are monkeys wearing suits that's all
we are
and uh we know next to nothing about the
universe we know less than five percent
of the of the universe so we should not
get carried away and think that we know
now everything and the universe is
infinite
from what we observed thus far in the
past
few decades
we have observed that the universe
appears to be remarkably flat
it could be something else we don't know
maybe it's a local
effect
and only in the visible universe maybe
there's something else out there which
we're not able to see and maybe there is
curvature that we don't know we don't
quite know
we know very little about the mysteries
of the universe but from what we
observed
the universe appears to be flat thus far
let's see how it goes
okay the naman gupta says can we we can
see stars in the sky with our naked eyes
but not galaxies
when they are millions of times bigger
why is this so
or is it that we can only see stars
within our galaxy with the naked eye
so when we look at the sky the stars
that we see are the stars that are
present in our galaxy
right
and galaxies are not millions of times
bigger than bigger than a star they are
billions
hundreds of billions of times bigger
than stars
but they are incredibly far away the
closest the nearest galaxy to the earth
the andromeda galaxy is about i don't
know
1.5 million
light years away from here that is
astonishingly far away and yet it is
visible actually let's take a look at uh
andromeda
night sky one second
let's see what the andromeda galaxy
looks like in the night sky it's
actually visible
me
share my screen
and show you what it looks like
take a look at this
so this is what
the night sky would look like
if the andromeda galaxy were brighter
the galaxy is quite faint it's not quite
visible like this if you make it
brighter then it will be actually
visible like this you can see the moon
and you can see andromeda which is
actually larger
as seen from the earth than the moon
right
but it's so far away that it's quite
faint and that's why it looks like a
smudgy
blob it's not quite visible but this is
the effect if it were not so damn it
would look it would look like this
now when it comes to other galaxies
which are much much further away they
are so far away that they look like
points to us they look like points it's
because of the enormous distances
involved that the galaxies look look so
small so when we look at the sky
it looks like it's just star stars but
many of these
stars could actually end up being
galaxies and that's what we discover
when you take take a telescope and look
at the sky and magnify various objects
and then these little points resolve
into galaxies
so we do see galaxies but they look like
points except for one or two like the
andromeda galaxy the andromeda galaxy
looks like a
fuzzy
cottony
little
smudged out blob but it's actually a
galaxy right so it's because because of
the enormous distances involved and the
andromeda galaxy is so far away 1.5
million light years away i think yeah
that it's quite faint so even though it
is visible as a disc is a side side on
disk it's quite faint so we can't really
tell that it's a galaxy you you make it
brighter using various techniques it
looks like a proper galaxy
eventually it's going to merge with our
galaxy so in the future it's going to be
much closer and it will look much larger
and much brighter in the future
and the thing is even our galaxy we
don't quite see it right
we have so much light pollution in the
cities on the surface of the earth that
we don't quite see our own galaxy even
though we are in the middle of it you go
in the middle of a forest where there
are no artificial lights you can see the
entire milky way side on it's incredible
so these are the reasons why we don't
quite see these things
okay vega says what does collapsing
under one's own gravity mean can you
explain this in layman's terms all right
uh layman's terms i try to explain
everything in layman's terms actually
so
um
what does collapsing under one's own
gravity mean so when you talk about
collapsing under one's own gravity we're
not talking about human beings
we typically
use this kind of language when you talk
about stars
we talk about stars collapsing under
their own gravity what does that mean
let's say you have a star that is let's
let's say 20 times
the mass of the sun
when you have a star of that size
it's going to every star
is a star because it it there is a
fusion reaction going on inside it a
star is
incredibly massive what is the mass of
the sun let me take a look at the mass
of the sun
sun
mass solar mass is 10 raised to 30
kilograms right
no it's uh
10 is 24 kilograms 33
yes something like that it's it's
enormously it's enormously massive right
and this enormous mass of the sun
creates
a ridiculous amount of pressure in the
inside of the sun now the the star is
mostly made up of hydrogen gas
hydrogen
and this pressure so if you go to the
bottom of the oceans in the earth
there is an incredible amount of
pressure from the water that's on top of
you if you go to the bottom of the
mariana trench in the philippines region
there is more than 11 or so kilometers
of water above you
and that exerts an enormous amount of
pressure or anything which is down there
you take a regular summer in there it's
gonna get crushed like a can of coke
yeah
so if that is the pressure of water
imagine the enormous pressure of this of
the sun
in on the interior of the sun
and this enormous pressure
causes atoms of hydrogen to fuse
together into helium and that is the
nuclear reaction that produces this
enormous amount of light and heat which
keeps us alive here on the earth right
so that is
what fuels the nuclear reaction the
fusion reaction
so there is gravity there is enormous
pressure
and yet the star doesn't collapse into a
point why is that so because of
something called the pauli exclusion
principle which applies which is a
quantum mechanical principle i will not
go into that layman's language what it
says is that
fermions are certain kind of particle
protons
protons neutrons electrons they cannot
occupy the same space
right and you try to squeeze them
together they're gonna push push back
and that is what causes this outward
pressure that resists the inward
collapse of a star
that's why a star remains circular and
it has a certain size it doesn't
collapse into itself right because of
the the powerli
exclusion principle and also because of
the uh nuclear reaction that produces
this outward
uh effect
this outward pressure so there's a
balance an equilibrium that causes a
star to have a certain size
now when you have a star that exceeds a
certain size let's say it's more than 20
times the mass of the sun
eventually all the hydrogen in the star
will be used up it will become helium
then
the helium atoms will start fusing
together and you will have the formation
of heavier and heavier elements
and all of these fusion reactions give
off
energy now eventually what happens is
that the star
will run out of heavier elements it will
start fusing iron
iron will start being produced in the
interior of the star and the fusion
reaction that produces iron
consumes more in energy than it gives
off
right
and therefore this heat source
disappears
the
the energy the outward pressure that
resists the inward collapse of the star
suddenly goes away the moment iron
starts forming inside a star
the star collapses upon itself
it's it's a very rapid collapse
so it will collapse upon itself and if
the mass of the star exceeds a certain
limit let's say more than 20 times i'm
just giving a rough ballpark figure if
it exceeds more than 20 times
the mass of the sun let's say
then nothing will be able to eventually
stop the collapse of the star bond
itself not even the power exclusion
principle not even the neutron neutron
degeneracy pressure that you see need to
neutron stars it will simply collapse
keep on collapsing until it becomes a
point
what's called a singularity
in general relativity in other words
the star will wink out and wink out
and become a black hole
that is what we mean by collapsing under
a star collapsing under its own gravity
in the case of the sun it's not massive
enough
so in the case of the sun eventually
what would be left behind after all the
fusion reactions is a massive
spherical
carbon crystal
a massive
very very hot
diamond
it's called a white dwarf it's going to
be very hot for a very long period of
time eventually it'll cool down it'll
stop glowing it'll become a black dwarf
so the sun will not be able to collapse
under its own gravity at the end of its
uh life cycle it will become a massive
ball of diamond a white dwarf
larger stars will collapse into neutron
stars uh everything so so everything is
given off and at the end you have a
neutron star at the the
end of the life cycle a neutron star is
an extremely ultra
compact atomic nucleus essentially just
neutrons with the crust of other protons
etc on the surface possibly we don't
quite know but that's what it's like
so neutron stars also don't collapse
under their own gravity but
certain stars provided they're large
enough do collapse under their own
gravity and they become black holes so
that's what we mean by this term
collapsing a star collapsing under its
own gravity
manmativari says i have never been much
interested in cosmology but this one
sentence i've heard very often from you
from me
and other astrophysicists death of a
star when a star dies blah blah blah
happens
if a star can die does it imply that a
star is a living entity
if yes is there a way with which we can
communicate with a star
do stars communicate with each other do
they have a social media do they have
social media
please pick this one i really want to
know okay
see
it's like this
when us when a scientist
wants to communicate with non-scientists
they cannot use mathematical equations
they cannot use scientific terminology
they have to use analogies
we talk about the evaporation of a black
hole no black holes don't actually
evaporate
it's not water vapor that comes out of
it but we use the term
black hole evaporation
and that is a term that we use
to communicate mostly with
non-scientists right
and similarly we use this term
the life and the death of a star it's
not a living entity
it it is not life as we know it
it's it's a nuclear reactor a fusion
reactor a massive
massive thermonuclear reaction that we
are witnessing in real time right that's
what a star is
so it's not life and death but it's it's
just
a certain kind of language that
scientists use to communicate
with non-scientists
because otherwise people don't get
interested if you
it's uninteresting if you use
mathematical equations and things like
that
in
scientific papers and publications
one typically sees different kind of
language right even there people would
scientists would write about life and
death life cycle etc it doesn't mean
actual life it's just the overall
existence
of a star in a certain state
and the transition from one state to
another one phase to another of its
existence right existence
so it's just a figure of speech it
doesn't mean that the star is a living
being
yeah
that's something you used to commute for
communication for making communication
effective and interesting if i start
using technical language with you and
scientific language with you you guys
will all
lose interest obviously because it will
make no sense right so that's why we use
such terms it doesn't mean that it's
actually alive but yeah good question
okay sameer says can we make
water artificially by combining hydrogen
and oxygen atoms
what is the progress of technology to
make artificial water
see if you combine hydrogen and oxygen
you we know the chemical composition of
water h2o two atoms of hydrogen one atom
of oxygen
you bring that together you have h2o
which is water molecules so that's not
artificial water that's actual water
you can do it shall i show you an
example of that in action
let me show you
so
hydrogen and oxygen
are excellent rocket
fuels
let me show you once again
so let me show you the production of
of
water in this manner
this space shuttle
if you can see it it's got this orangish
tank
this orangish tank contains used to
contain
liquefied hydrogen and liquefied oxygen
and the exothermic reaction
gave rise to nothing but water
so if you see all of this what looks
like
smoke it's not smoke
much of it is water vapor
so in the space shuttle actually you
have two boosters also these booster
engines these boosters are
on the two sides those are
solid fuel
rockets so those contain some chemical
which i'm not sure what it is you can
look it up
but the
but the space shuttle itself if you see
it it has got three engines
those engines they use liquefied
hydrogen and liquefied oxygen and they
give off water vapor yeah so that is one
of the ways in which you can combine
hydrogen and oxygen atoms and produce
water vapor water in an exothermic
reaction
so yes to answer your question it can be
done you can make water artificially by
taking hydrogen taking oxygen maybe
liquefied hydrogen liquefied oxygen
bringing them together igniting them
with a spark
and producing water vapor it's possible
why would you do it
don't we have enough water readily
available on the planet
we have abundant
uh reserves of water in the oceans
we have a lot of groundwater and rain
water and whatnot
yeah why do we need to do this it is
certainly possible to do it but what is
the need to do it it is incredibly
expensive to produce water in this
manner
you have to
have liquefied hydrogen which is
extremely difficult to produce extremely
expensive to produce you need to have
pure liquefied oxygen again incredibly
difficult and expensive to produce you
need to maintain them at cryogenic
temperatures very cold temperatures you
bring them together explosively which is
a very dangerous thing why do that
why do that
so it can be done definitely i just
showed you it's it's done but it's a
very
very very
hot exothermic reaction and there's no
need to do that just
take the water that's available on the
planet in incredibly large quantities in
great abundance and use that
so
so that's a more
cost effective efficient
and practical way
of
acquiring water
instead of creating water artificially
current says what is archaeoastronomy
uh rq astronomy well this is
well yeah okay
so rq astronomy is the
science of deciphering ancient
astronomical data
like thousands of years old
so for ex instance let me show you an
example of that oldest
supernova
uh let me share my screen
so for instance there was this there is
this rock inscription in northern india
in
this is what it looks like
it's this rock inscription was drawn was
carved on a rock in northern india in
kashmir i believe
about six 000 years ago
and it shows
two guys hunting there's a deer and
there are two suns in the sky
right
two sons not one son two sons
so uh
so it was uh somebody got the bright
idea that this may represent a supernova
in the night sky
and so
scientists in the tata institute of
phenomenal research mumbai tif or mumbai
they they looked it up they did some
kind of analysis
and they discovered that it this
represents a supernova that happened
about 6000 years ago
and i don't remember what the name of
the supernova is but you can look it up
in the
in this article
it's not two suns it's the sun
and it is a supernova which would have
appeared as almost as bright as the sun
and that's why it was drawn in this
manner right
so this is an example of
archaeoastronomy
ancient records of astronomical events
that are recorded either on rock or in
ancient
literature ancient texts
and you take that
and you use uh
astronomical calculations using
celestial mechanics etc and you try to
date
those events when did these events
happen based on the
uh astronomical
data that is embedded in the texts so
that is rq astronomy it can be
very uh
accurate provided you translate or
interpret
the text properly
if you don't interpret it properly
you're going to end up with all kinds of
incorrect inferences and so on and there
are certain issues in rq astronomy for
instance when it comes to comets
when there is let's say a 3000 year old
text that says a certain comet was in a
certain location in the sky and so of
time the thing about comets
is that their path changes
comets are and they have unstable
trajectories because
they are they they give off gas
when they are heated by the sun
and the gas jets can occur in different
directions and because the jets can
can occur in random directions the
trajectory the path of the comet can
change it's unpredictable
so you cannot
reliably and accurately use comets
for archaeological uh predictions and
analysis and so on so that in short
in brief in a nutshell is what our
astronomy is
vishal says what could possibly be in
the center of our universe are there any
theories regarding this
the center of the universe right
so this essentially
can be
reformulated this question can be
reformulated to ask
where did the big bang take place we
know
that the universe the best theory
that explains
the observable universe is the big bang
theory right
the so called big bang theory which says
that the entire universe
originated in a singularity or what was
close to a singularity which expanded
outwards
in what is called the big bang and that
gave rise eventually to the universe
that we live in
so many people ask this question where
did the big bang take place
well
it took place everywhere the entire
universe was compressed into
an infinite infinitesimally small region
of space into a infinite infinitesimally
small point
so everything that's here was inside
that which means when the big bang
happened
it happened everywhere which means there
is no center of the universe if you want
to think of some place as a center of
the universe it's where you are
you
you my dear viewer
are the center of the universe from your
perspective from my perspective i am the
center of the universe and so on
so every point
in the universe as far as you know i
just i just spoke about this a few
minutes ago
that the universe seems to be remarkably
flat
which could indicate indicate that it
possibly could be infinite
if you have an infinite universe it's
mostly unlikely but let's say it's an
infinite universe if it is infinite then
any point in the universe is a center
right
so you could say
and if you look at the observable
universe
which is a spherical region of space
that we can observe
from our vantage point we are at the
center of the observable universe so
the best answer i can offer you
is that you
are the center of your universe i am the
center of my universe and the earth
our vantage point is the center this is
the actual center of the observable
universe all right that's not a theory
it's a fact
ananya says how
would you compare quantum mechanics to
einstein's theory of relativity which do
you think is more accurate and what
would be a joining a bridge between them
okay how do you compare these two
theories these are incredibly successful
theories first of all
and extremely accurate the most accurate
the most successful theory that we do
have
is quantum field theory
which is an advanced version of quantum
mechanics right
it is second quantization and field
quantization and so on
so
it is incredibly accurate
and all the technology that we enjoy
today
is
the result of our understanding of the
quantum world the ultra microscopic
world
from which our physical reality emerges
right so that is quantum mechanics
quantum field theory it is the
theory
of the
incredibly small
uh
domain the ultra microscopic world sub
atom atomic and sub the atoms nuclei sub
atomic particles you know protons
neutrons electrons quarks
the various fields
and so on that is
quantum mechanics or quantum field
theory the theory of the ultra
microscopic universe from which
our
lived reality emerges
einstein's theory of relativity is also
the theory of the universe on large
scales it's the theory
of the large-scale universe
you know
so when we talk about quantum theory
it's about ultra-microscopic scales
when you talk about
relativity it's large scales
light years
parsecs megaparsecs and so on the very
large scale structure of the universe on
those scales you have
einstein's general theory of relativity
which is
which is curved space time
geometry dynamics that's what it is
four dimensional
space space time
so these two theories are
tested they are proven scientists have
been trying to disprove them
experimentally for decades
thousands of different kinds of tests
have been done
and they have all
failed these theories work they are
valid but we do know
that they somehow don't mix
because when we look at quantum theory
there is no gravity in there
gravity doesn't figure in there
and time itself is an external dimension
it's a classical parameter in quantum
theory time t
yeah in the equations
so
there are certain limitations when it
comes to quantum theory time
is still a mystery we don't know what
time is time doesn't emerge out of
quantum theory
and gravitation doesn't even exist in
quantum theory you try to bring
gravitation into it it breaks down
gravity doesn't work
in in the ultra microscopic world there
is no need for for gravity in quantum
mechanics somehow
and
you try to you try to quantize gravity
it it it doesn't work you know and there
are very clear ways in which which it
doesn't work you try to create let's say
let's say you try to construct a black
hole
through quantum mechanics you can do it
you can construct a mathematical black
hole
in the ultra microscopic domain
you can take
um
a pure mass a point particle of pure
mass and and use the rules of quantum
mechanics to create a black hole it will
be different from the black holes that
general theory
the general theory of relativity gives
us very different
the
schrodinger radius
is
it doesn't figure in a quantum black
hole it's a different kind of radius
that you get there and so on
so there are differences and these two
theories somehow
we are unable to reconcile them
so i don't have an answer as to what
would be a joining bridge between them
we need to find somehow a way of
quantizing gravity
we still don't have it people have been
trying for a long time that's why string
theory became a thing we're trying to
figure out a new way of doing this and
the string theory has not solved any
problems so these are two very different
theories
one is about the ultra microscopic world
from which reality emerges the other is
about the large scale structure of
reality both work extremely well but
there is a disconnect between the two
and the disconnect is apparent when we
try to look at black holes
in the
quantum domain if that's why you get
these singularities you know these
infinity which is which is division by
zero which is unphysical
when you have a singularity it tells you
it's telling you that your equation has
broken down it is giving you an
unphysical result
so we have singularities in general
relativity which tells you that the
equations of general relativity break
down at the ultra microscopic scale
which means we need better equations
which means we need to amend the theory
somehow in such a way that it works
at the quantum scale as of today we
don't have answers that is the situation
as of today the 21st century was
supposed to be the century in which we
figured out what gravity is
uh in the last 22 years we have made not
one inch of progress that's where we are
and that's why physics is so interesting
because there is so much to discover
all right
abhishek says what is mass
what is the difference between mass and
weight
what is mass and what is the difference
between mass and weight mass essentially
is the amount of matter
in a body
let's say you have
a ball
that contains one kilogram of
mass you take that
ball
you put it on the surface of the earth
it will weigh one kilogram here
you take it to the moon
it will weigh one sixth
of the of the weight that it has on on
earth so the amount of matter
inside that ball is the same
but if it is on the surface of the earth
it will weigh one kilogram if it is on
the surface of the moon it will weigh
one sixth of a kilogram you take it to
jupiter it will have a different weight
you take it to saturn it will have a
different weight you take it to pluto it
will have a different weight and so on
so weight is the effect of gravity on a
mass
and mass is the amount of matter
that is contained in a body
another way of looking at mass is its
equivalent energy by e equals m c
squared
so you can convert mass into
energy
generally we talk about electron volts
kev mev gev etcetera kilo electron volts
mega electron volts and so on which is
the equivalent energy of a of a certain
mass
so a mass remains the same but its
weight changes depending on where it is
so that is roughly
the difference between mass and weight
okay pranav says as you said earlier
mathematics is the language of physics
and i'm trying to self-study physics so
it would be great if you could recommend
what are the different types of
mathematics necessary to understand
physics in brief and are there any book
recommendations by you
uh
the mathematics that you need for
physics
you essentially
um
need to know a lot of math
math is like a toolkit which you need to
solve problems in physics so you would
need to know infinite series power
series complex numbers linear algebra
calculus differentiation integration
partial differentiation partial
integrals multiple integrals
ordinary differential equations partial
differential equations vector analysis
tensor analysis
fourier series power series calculus of
variations special functions
series solutions of differential
equations legendre functions
bessel functions hermet polynomials
lager functions partial differential
equations like i said
functions of a complex variable
probability statistics
the whole lot that's a whole lot of math
that you need to know
in order
to actually do physics
without math you can't do physics you
need to master all of these different
areas of math
would i recommend any books
well if you know the basics if you
the college level or something or
university level i would recommend
mathematical methods of physics by mary
bose and there is a
i have a bunch of books here uh mary
bose is a is a good
place to start off with or you could
take any of these topics and pick up the
sham strom series book
for these topics and then work out all
the problems and you get good at that
and that's how you get good at physics
once you go deep into mathematics you
will realize you're actually doing
physics because
math is the language of physics for
instance if you take the book on pa on
on
differential equations by ten and bomb
and pollard you go deeper into it you'll
realize that the problems you're solving
are physics problems
that's how it is
so yes math is the language of physics
you need to build your own massive
toolkit you need to understand lots of
different kind of math different
branches of math
and only if you do that can you actually
do physics
at the
at the level of the big boys or big
girls
math is the difference between
the grown-ups and the kids
you can understand understand physics
conceptually you can speak about physics
and talk physics and discuss physics and
all that but you can't do physics
unless you're good at math so you got to
do it
okay sachin says stephenson 218 is the
biggest star that has been discovered
thus far
is there a possibility
that it has its own solar system if yes
would its solar system have a lot of
planets since its solar mass is so much
so this star is apparently the largest
star that has ever been discovered
millions of times more massive than the
sun
its
diameter
is it's its radius is so big
that if that star where where the sun is
today
then its surface
would
would exceed
the uh the
orbit of saturn
so
in case you know
the planets in our solar system are
mercury venus
earth mars
saturn jupiter uranus neptune pluto
so that star would engulf the orbit of
saturn
and if you want to look at what this
star would look like compared to the sun
let me show you a nice image
let me show you
a comparison
take a look at this
so stephenson 218 is on the right and
the sun is a small little dot on the
left over here
that is how enormous
this star is
so that's what stephenson 218 looks like
it's called a hyper giant star it's
i mean it's at the limit of how large a
star can get
now the thing about these hyper giant
stars
is that they are so massive that they
burn out their nuclear fuel
very very rapidly the sun our sun
has a lifetime lifetime
of about 10
billion years
10 billion
a hyper giant like stephens and
something 6218
would have a lifetime of about a few
million years only it's a very
short-lived star extremely shorted star
if it is so short-lived
most likely there's not even time enough
time for planets to form around it or if
planets do form around it they would be
very rudimentary
very very hot
proto-planets
and eventually the star will die most
likely in a supernova hypernova or
something maybe i'm not quite sure what
is the life cycle of this sort of star
what is the end stage but yeah if there
is a solar system
most likely it's just debris very hot
debris it is very unlikely for planets
to form in such a short period of time
if planet planets do form those will be
very hot and very rudimentary balls of
fire or lava that's what it would be
like and that's all it is
all right
okay my friends uh we are at the end of
the questions let me take some questions
from the live chat
you have questions
ask me now
on the live chat i will take a few
questions before we
end
this session
so
dunga singh johan my views on the new
monkey box i have no idea what it is
um
every
few months a new virus comes into the
picture
yeah
i i don't have any views i don't think
it's a serious issue
when do you think our civilization will
reach the second scale in the kardashev
scale maybe in the next hundred thousand
years
if we survive that long maybe never we
don't know
it's it's just pure speculation we don't
quite know
does the double split slate experiment
prove the existence of maya that vedanta
talks about
what exactly collapses the wave function
a conscious observer
we don't know
what collapses the wave function there
are different theories about what
collapses the wave function
is it consciousness that causes collapse
is it something else that causes
collapse
there are experiments in which there is
no conscious observer the observer is
just a mechanical apparatus and yet the
wave function collapses so we don't know
maya i mean
you you cannot make spirituality and
religion and faith with science
you can't do it i think i have to keep
repeating this for the rest of my life
yeah you cannot mix science and
spirituality don't mix science and
religion don't mix
science and philosophy don't mix
science is about observable observables
in maya and all this how do you define
maya from the scientific perspective so
let's not mix vedanta in science i have
the highest amount of respect for our
culture for vedanta but it doesn't mix
with science science is different we
india is the birthplace of science
we know that right
and our scientists
did not mix
faith with science otherwise you can't
do science so please my dear friends
please understand this you can't mix
these things
okay let's take some other questions
a few other questions
oh i can see some questions that have
been answered already very recently
um
uh
okay sir thank you so much i am greatly
enlightened thank you vedam in science
all right thank you
no there is no way to prove that souls
exist
you can't
can you measure a soul can you observe a
soul can you can you
do is there a clear scientific
definition of a soul is the soul an
observable entity
measurable entity it's not right
it's an unphysical
entity
and therefore you cannot talk about
souls in science
and therefore you can't prove it you
either believe in it or you don't
but
you can't prove it
it is non-falsifiable
all right let's take some
questions from science
okay as the galaxies are so far away
what is there between galaxies you have
empty space between galaxies it's mostly
vacuum and you have the cosmic microwave
background relief radiation the relic
radiation which is left over from the
big bang you could call it the you could
consider it to it to be the after glow
of the big bang which is extremely cold
radiation
2.75
degrees kelvin just barely above zero
kelvin right
and you have
what is almost vacuum but that vacuum is
not empty it's steaming with virtual
particle anti-particle pairs which you
will understand if you study
uh
quantum field theory so it's empty space
but that empty space is not quite empty
it's actually teaming with particle
anti-particle pairs virtual
particle anti-particle pairs
that's what lies between galaxies so
from our perspective it's just empty
space empty space very very very
uh very thin
diffused you you would see some protons
cosmic ray protons antiprotons etc
flying around a few sometimes atoms of
hydrogen perhaps but very few and far
between it's an almost perfect vacuum
okay what next
um
please
answer sir what would you like me to
answer sir
what if the sun is suddenly replaced by
a black hole
well we would not know for about eight
minutes
after eight minutes the light will
disappear because it takes eight minutes
for the light
to travel from the sun to the earth so
if the light stops
being emitted from the sun it will take
eight minutes for us to know and after
that after that
it will be darkness
but the earth will remain in orbit
around this new object
the black hole and provided the black
hole that has the same mass as its as
the sun
then none of the orbits
of the various planets and other bodies
in the solar system would change they
would stay exactly the same and nothing
else would happen the only thing that
will change is that the light source
will disappear and everything will
freeze
and that's what happens nothing else
okay um
a couple more questions
does infinity exist in the real world
infinity is actually unphysical
let me give you a different perspective
infinities do exist
and infinities of different sizes
think about it like this
how many numbers do we have
between
and
construct 10
number line
start with zero zero one two three four
five all the way up to ten
we have ten numbers
between zero and ten it's it's from zero
to ten right but
between zero and one
you have all the decimals right zero
point one zero point zero zero point
three between zero and zero point one
you have further decimals zero point
zero one zero point zero two so between
any two numbers there is an infinite
number of numbers
between 0 and 1 there is an infinite
between 0 and 10 also there is an
infinite number of numbers and these two
infinities have different sizes
don't they
isn't that
perplexing
isn't that strange but it's true
so infinities do exist
mathematically at least
and infinities are not all equal
infinities coming can come in different
sizes some infinities are larger some
infiniti are smaller
so that's how it is that is a strange
thing about science and mathematics
sir let's discuss about james webb
telescope in detail what's its purpose
i think i have already discussed in
detail
its purpose is to give us a much more
detailed understanding of the universe
in
the infrared domain
it will allow us to look deeper into the
universe look further back in time
because the hubble telescope
did not have the ability
to uh
to observe the universe in infrared
wavelengths
and because of the expansion of the
universe
which is still continuing the oldest
light in the universe which was about
230 or so million years after the big
bang the oldest side of the universe
which was emitted at that time
it has been stretched out
beyond the visible wavelengths into the
infrared wavelengths
so the hubble space telescope simply
cannot see that old light
the james webb space telescope can see
it
it is
purpose built
to observe the universe in the infrared
spectrum right and that's why it's going
to be able to look back further in time
than the hubble space telescope so that
is the purpose it's going to give us a
much sharper
uh image
of various
objects it observes we are already
seeing that and it's going to be able to
show us
galaxies
that are the possibly the first galaxies
that ever formed
so we will get a whole different
perspective on the universe right
so i have discussed that in multiple
episodes you need to look at that i've
also spoken about the damage that
suffered in this episode itself
and i have discussed the images in the
previous episode one of the previous
episodes look at that please all right
sir
okay is there anything else
what if the himalayas did not exist if
they did not exist they would not exist
is the moon artificial
the rotation of the moon of the earth is
real mysterious
the distance between the moon and its
satellite is very large compared to
other planets
which satellite does the moon have
what's the evidence that the moon is
artificial do you have any evidence that
somebody made it that maybe some
government made it
let's see something else um
[Laughter]
what if humans did not exist then we
would not be having this discussion
all right i think we are done
ruchika says it got damaged yes i have
spoken about this at least twice in this
episode yes it got damaged
very minor damage it's going to be fine
okay my dear friends we are done we are
at the end of today's episode thank you
very much for your questions and i will
see you in the next episode until then
take care thank you again
and
see you very soon bye